<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-11T12:39:17+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">the journal of francis billones</title><subtitle>pseudo-intellectual rants about tech and society</subtitle><entry><title type="html">unqualified and unpolished thoughts on capitalism</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/11/11/unqualified-thoughts-on-capitalism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="unqualified and unpolished thoughts on capitalism" /><published>2024-11-11T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-11T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/11/11/unqualified-thoughts-on-capitalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/11/11/unqualified-thoughts-on-capitalism.html">&lt;p&gt;tl;dr: capitalism is not inherently flawed, and pursuing profits is not inherently evil.
it is a game, and when evil is legal in the game, you cannot blame winners for playing optimally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought of this while sitting in a lecture about faith and capitalism. The message being
communicated by the professor was quite honestly not bad on its own—the same old
“we have to think about God and morality when making business decisions”. Obviously
not a bad philosophy for running companies, and I can certainly think of a few that ought
to do that more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I thought about it a little deeper, though, I realized that it is quite literally
impossible to do that in real life, outside of an ethics professors’ utopia where
everyone acts in everyone else’s best interest. This is not a dig at ethics professors,
by the way—every field has its own utopia upon which it bases its teachings upon. Economics
assumes everyone thinks rationally when making economic decisions, and programmers assume
people actually care about performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kidding aside, the notion that entities in a capitalist system must follow &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; basic
moral philosophy to not delve into anarchy and chaos is not something new nor novel. Obviously,
Apple would obviously &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; to kill every competitor it had, but it can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It becomes a little harder to distinguish between what is moral and what isn’t when we
talk about actions that don’t drive deep into our primitive natures. Killing is something
that no one would like to see, nor do (and if you do, there’s a medical term for you). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2024/2/9/24067957/apple-right-to-repair-oregon-bill-parts-pairing-ban&quot;&gt;Making
specialized hardware that can’t be fixed by an independent technician&lt;/a&gt; is something that we
unfortunately didn’t have to evolve an aversion to, and so lives in a much grayer area
ethically speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, when companies commit egregious sins against humanity, it is (and &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; is)
in pursuit of profits. This is the main driver of capitalism—fierce competition starves
the weak and unoptimal and rewards the strong and efficient. Obviously, this formula works.
Advancements in technology, logistics, and manufacturing that make the world as abundant
as it is today is a direct result of capitalism’s competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pursuit of abundance, players in the capitalist game throw away morality in favor
of efficiency. Nestlé is allegedly &lt;a href=&quot;https://forloveofwater.org/water-privatization-the-struggle-to-stop-nestles-groundwater-grab-continues/&quot;&gt;privatizing water&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/inflation-shrinkflation-skimpflation-toilet-paper-candy-cereal-lendingtree/&quot;&gt;shrinkflation&lt;/a&gt; has led to consumers paying more
for the same product, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2023/02/01/1152893248/red-cobalt-congo-drc-mining-siddharth-kara&quot;&gt;“modern day slavery”&lt;/a&gt; is
happening in regions of South Africa rich with rare earth metals used in the manufacturing of batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is capitalism inherently flawed? A lot of people seem to think so, but I think (and I think
this is the view most people arrive at) that with an adequate system of checks and balances, as well
as good policy enforcement, a lot of these problems can be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you rolling your eyes, yes—having a good controlling body that regulates
a capitalist system is an entire problem on its own. However, I think a lot of the discord around
this topic comes from a disproportionate amount of attention being paid towards the evil
actions of companies that are simply acting in their own best interests according to the
rules of the game.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">tl;dr: capitalism is not inherently flawed, and pursuing profits is not inherently evil. it is a game, and when evil is legal in the game, you cannot blame winners for playing optimally.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">generative ai: generational implications</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/09/25/generative-ai-generational-implications.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="generative ai: generational implications" /><published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/09/25/generative-ai-generational-implications</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/09/25/generative-ai-generational-implications.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to E.J.M.M for contributing to this article&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative AI is a branch of artificial intelligence that can produce content across various mediums, such as text, images, video, and audio. The most popular forms of generative AI include “large language models” or LLMs such as ChatGPT and Gemini AI, as well as “text-to-image” models such as DALL-E 3 and Midjourney. These tools produce text and visuals that are nearly indistinguishable from those created by humans. Advances in multi-modality—a quality of AI models to interpret and generate content in multiple mediums rather than just one—have greatly expanded the capabilities and improved the ease-of-use of generative AI products. For example, ChatGPT is capable of processing and generating documents and images, alongside its typical text-based prompts. As a result, the popularity of AI tools has skyrocketed in recent years. 70% of Gen Z report using the technology, among which 52% cite using Generative AI to make informed decisions&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salesforce.com/news/stories/generative-ai-statistics/&quot;&gt;[s]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. With wide-scale adoption among the youth, it is becoming increasingly urgent for the education sector to develop strategies and policies for accommodating AI within the curriculum and to encourage its ethical and responsible use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before generative AI, plagiarism has been a prevalent problem in academic writing since time immemorial. With the advent of the World Wide Web, academic text from all disciplines and geographies have never been so accessible; what used to require going to a library and sifting through dusty collections of books and papers is now available anywhere to anyone with an internet connection. As such, the creation and implementation of protocols for the prevention, detection, and punishment of plagiarism became essential to every academic institution around the world. The consequences of plagiarism in most university policies are universally severe, ranging from a mere failing grade in very generous cases, to outright expulsion. Countless tools and software have been developed for the automatic detection of plagiarism, from exclusive in-house solutions to commercially available products such as Turnitin and Grammarly. The market for plagiarism detection software even before the pandemic and generative AI was by no means tiny—Turnitin’s parent company was acquired for $1.8 billion on March 6, 2019 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.turnitin.com/press/advance-to-acquire-turnitin&quot;&gt;[s]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Immense time, manpower, and funding was invested just to limit plagiarism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities and academic institutions around the world are now facing a similar—if not bigger—problem in generative AI. What used to require the already limited effort of finding suitable material and paraphrasing is now available with one well-written prompt. Generative AI serves as an all-purpose tool for the expert manipulation of language; it is a search engine, writer, and paraphraser in one package. It can also play the role of a teacher, a consultant, and a research adviser&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lindif.2023.102274&quot;&gt;[s]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike plagiarism, preventing the use of  generative AI is much less straightforward. Plagiarism detection software is built around “text similarity”&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1001.3487&quot;&gt;[s]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, an established and well-researched problem in natural language processing with many approaches depending on the application. Plagiarism detectors benefit from having a limited “search space”—that is to say, they only require a diverse database of texts, which are finite in nature. Text that passes a plagiarism detector is either an original piece of work, or a well-paraphrased and edited version of an original piece of work, both of which are nonproblems. On the other hand, generative AI is fully capable of automating the process of producing original text, rendering text similarity obsolete. Thus, a different approach must be taken. “AI detectors” such as Quillbot (which was previously a popular paraphrasing tool) gained popularity early on due to their claims of being able to distinguish AI-generated text and human-written text. However, several controversies generated question marks around their authority. False positives were rampant—genuine student-written texts were being falsely flagged as AI-generated. When fed text from the Bible or from scientific papers, those were also flagged as AI-generated. False positives in AI detectors are significantly more harmful than those in plagiarism detectors, because they cannot be manually verified&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanderbilt.edu/brightspace/2023/08/16/guidance-on-ai-detection-and-why-were-disabling-turnitins-ai-detector/&quot;&gt;[s]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A plagiarism detector’s false positive can be manually rechecked against the claimed source material and left up to the professor’s discretion. The same cannot be said for AI detectors, which are based on statistics and heuristics, and therefore cannot serve as valid evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With detection being established as an exercise in futility, it is safe to say that generative AI is here to stay. However, the educational system cannot bury its head in the sand. Avoiding change and retaining the same outdated practices for teaching will simply lead to said practices easily being taken advantage of by LLMs. The use of LLMs is not necessarily malicious; they have a myriad of other applications, which include helping in all parts of the writing process—suggesting ideas, drafting outlines, paraphrasing, and proofreading, as well as providing personalized instant feedback, something that is difficult to achieve with large class sizes. They can also explain concepts with a thoroughness that human teachers might not necessarily have the time nor patience for. All of these are capabilities that would add value to the pedagogical process, and it would be remiss to neglect them. Instead, it will be more beneficial for teachers and professors to modify their classes with these tools in mind. The calculator may have reduced the value of mental math skills, but no one is arguing that calculators ruin math education. Math is more than just arithmetic—it is about understanding abstract concepts and combining these concepts in a creative manner to solve problems and derive new mathematical ideas. Writing can be likened to arithmetic, where basic proficiency can easily be taught without the use of calculators. Beyond that, creativity and originality should reign supreme, and no amount of artificial intelligence trained to simply mimic human tendencies can ever surpass that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of generative AI marks a possible paradigm shift in the manner with which we conduct education. Students will now have access to an automated teacher that will perform any task that they want. If this fact is avoided, education will grow redundant as outdated curriculums will be taken advantage of by LLMs. However, if schools and universities embrace generative AI and build the education system around it, then the benefits of generative AI can be enjoyed and education can evolve and push the boundaries of what humans are intellectually capable of.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Special thanks to E.J.M.M for contributing to this article</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">identity and self expression</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/07/25/identity-and-self-expression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="identity and self expression" /><published>2024-07-25T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-07-25T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/07/25/identity-and-self-expression</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/07/25/identity-and-self-expression.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/identity-and-self-expression/the-wolf-of-wall-street.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Wolf of Wall Street” is a 2014 movie based on the 2007 memoir written by Jordan Belfort, former stockbroker and financial criminal. The movie stars Leonardo DeCaprio as Belfort’s character, following his journey from being a regular old stockbroker on the trading floor, to running boiler-room-style scams on penny stocks, to performing elaborate pump-and-dump schemes from his own brokerage house, Stratton Oakmont.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from telling the story of Belfort’s financial crimes, the movie also displays the other, much more “entertaining” aspects of his life: hookers, drugs, and cars and boats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/identity-and-self-expression/drugs-on-someones-butt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this has nothing to do with “Wall Street” and more to do with “The Wolf”. However, the aesthetics of this movie, as well as the personality and mannerisms of Leonardo DeCaprio’s character have massive influences on the public image and perception of Wall Street as well as the world of finance as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/identity-and-self-expression/finance-bro.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotyping is and has been a natural social phenomenon ever since we became homo sapiens. Reducing people from creatures of immense depth and complexity to simple patterns of behavior and tendencies allows our small monkey brains to grasp the concept of a “person” much more easily and efficiently. Being able to predict and model the behavior of other people is incredibly valuable — it allows one to develop trust to other people, as well as perform in a social environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we spend more and more time with a person, we do away with remembering them as a collection of different stereotypes and our mental model of them becomes much more natural and human. That is why we treat people we’ve known our entire lives differently — aside from the emotional connection, they are simply more “human” in our heads. Any stranger may as well be a video game NPC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotypes are informed and derived from the copying and mimicing of small micro-behaviors, characteristics, tendencies, and values across a group of people. Accents are an example of a characteristic that may form part of a larger stereotype. Combine an Indian accent and an Internet/over-the-phone scam, and you arrive at the infamous “Indian scammer” stereotype. When you think of a “hippie” (or at least, when an American thinks of a hippie), you typically picture a person with long hair, wearing brightly colored rainbow clothing, plays the guitar, maybe owns a van, is anti-war, and smokes marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This begs the question: Why do stereotypes fit so well? Humans are, after all, complex beings. We all have our own interests, needs, desires, and dreams. We were all raised differently and we have all had different experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible explanation for why this happens has to do with “being predictable”. Compressing people to mere concepts and patterns doesn’t necessarily just go one way. People themselves can start to compress their own personalities, in order to fit into an existing societal mold that they choose for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Predictability in game theory&lt;/summary&gt;
In a typical prisoners&apos; dilemma type scenario, the optimal action is always to not cooperate. However, when it comes to repeated prisoners&apos; dilemma scenarios, as is usually the case in real-life environments, cooperation is achieved faster when the two agents can feasibly predict one another. Learn more from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mScpHTIi-kM&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; Veritasium video.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since stereotypes are a tool for us to possibly infer or predict characteristics of a person from their other tendencies, if a person desires to be seen or to be interpreted as possibly having certain characteristics desirable to themselves, then they will adjust themselves to conform to “stereotypes”, ideas, and molds that fit those characteristics. For example, someone that values modesty, minimalism, and humility may express those values in the way they dress. This is the simplest form of self-expression — directly connecting ones actions to the values one holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, complexity and confusion arises when self-expression is derived not from the values, but from other expressions of those values themselves. For example, take Andrew Tate, an internet personality most known for his patriarchal values. Someone that agrees and takes inspiration from Tates’ views on mens’ role in society, womens’ value, and discipline, may, in a subconscious attempt to express their ideology, adopt other traits of Tate that aren’t necessarily connected to Tates’ original ideas; namely, his mannerisms, the way he dresses, his obsession with Bugattis, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be weak connections between those traits and the original ideas Tate expresses — speaking in a bold, arrogant manner may represent the idea of male strength that Tate values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is here where stereotypes and the value of inferring a person’s personality and values from their outward self-expression start to prove less useful. It is here where stereotypes do the most damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When expressions of values start to detach from the values themselves, unnecessary false equivalence and self-limitation occurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, tattoos in Western society are discriminated against, specifically because tattoos are typically associated with people from a lower socio-economic bracket. As such, because of the stigma surrounding them, tattoos also developed to be associated with rebellion. On the other hand, the art of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stu.ca/lnap/henna-its-history-and-cultural-significance/&quot;&gt;Henna&lt;/a&gt;” — the practice of staining the skin with a plant-based paste — has been practiced in Pakistan, India, Africa, and the Middle East for over 5000 years. Fundamentally speaking, they are no different — they are both done for the purposes of decorating the skin with figures. However, Henna is regarded with much more elegance and respect. It is only in Western society that a false equivalence was created — that tattoos, by virtue of their popularity among the lower class, are inherently “dirty”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the internet and the increasingly globalized nature of the world, the rate at which any one person (or at least, a person fortunate enough to have internet access or any form of electronic communication) discovers and experiences new things rival that of monarchs from the past world. As such, each of us have an incredible opportunity to become human beings with extreme depth and substance. It will be a waste to worry so much about fitting into an arbitrary social box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/identity-and-self-expression/cute.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details open=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
Korean actor Ma Dong-seok showing off his Hello Kitty merchandise. Fake &quot;masculine&quot; men can&apos;t say anything, because, well, look at the guy. He&apos;s buff and tough and no amount of Hello Kitty will ever take away from that.
&lt;/details&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the rabbit hole of personal finance</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/07/24/the-rabbit-hole-of-personal-finance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the rabbit hole of personal finance" /><published>2024-07-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/07/24/the-rabbit-hole-of-personal-finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2024/07/24/the-rabbit-hole-of-personal-finance.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve become semi-obsessed (slight exaggeration) with finance topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This started with and was a result of finally being able to withdraw all the allowance I had accumulated over years of studying at Philippine Science High School. My allowance money from those 6 years was a respectable 6 figures, and I was looking for a place to park it, and maybe earn some additional cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first place I turned to was BPI Savings. This was the bank my family transacted with for all of their savings accounts, personal loans, business loans, and investments. BPI is a large and ubiquitious bank in the Philippines, so naturally, I wanted to store my money with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when I looked at the interest rates on their savings accounts, I saw that they were a measley &lt;strong&gt;0.0925%&lt;/strong&gt;. Now, when I first saw this figure, it meant nothing to me — I wasn’t knowledgeable about typical savings account interest rates. However, I did know that the yearly inflation in the Philippines was well above that. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://psa.gov.ph/price-indices/cpi-ir&quot;&gt;Philippine Statistics Authority&lt;/a&gt;(PSA), the year-to-date headline inflation rate (as of the time of writing) is &lt;strong&gt;3.5%&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s &lt;strong&gt;37.8&lt;/strong&gt; times greater than the interest rate offered by BPI’s #SaveUp Peso Savings account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meant that if I simply parked my money in a typical BPI savings account, it would be decaying &lt;strong&gt;37.8&lt;/strong&gt; times faster than it would be growing — a mind boggling fact for me. If I did nothing, assuming a &lt;strong&gt;3.5%&lt;/strong&gt; inflation rate for &lt;strong&gt;20&lt;/strong&gt; years, the value of my cash would be HALVED.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I didn’t want this to happen. I did more research, and I stumbled upon Maya — a former digital payments-only service known as PayMaya turned digital payments and banking service. I was especially intrigued by the interest rates they were promoting — &lt;strong&gt;3.5%&lt;/strong&gt; base interest rate &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; by putting the money into a Maya Savings account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;How does Maya offer such a higher rate?&lt;/summary&gt;
Maya Bank is known as a &quot;digital bank&quot;, a type of bank that exists completely digitally and operates no physical branches. As such, the costs associated with running physical branches as well as servicing the needs of physical cash such as transporting cash to branches and ATM machines are completely non-existent. This allows Maya to transfer their savings on operating costs to the consumer, in the form of higher interest rates. In the future, if digital banks succeed in dominating a large part of the market, expect rates to lower as the need for customer acquisition lessens.
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Notes on computation&lt;/summary&gt;
The following figures are computed without considering the 20% tax on interest earnings, as well as inflation rates, mostly because I am lazy.
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Institution&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Account&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Interest Rate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;10-year return on P1m&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;BPI&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bpi.com.ph/personal/bank/deposits/deposit-rates-savings-and-checking&quot;&gt;#SaveUp Peso Savings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0925%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;P1,009,288.60&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;BDO&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bdo.com.ph/personal/accounts/savings/peso-savings/atm-savings&quot;&gt;Peso Savings ATM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0625%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;P1,006,267.61&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MetroBank&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metrobank.com.ph/accounts/savings&quot;&gt;Regular Savings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.0625%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;P1,006,267.61&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;LBP&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.landbank.com/cards/atm-savings-account&quot;&gt;ATM Savings Account&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.05%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;P1,005,011.27&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Maya&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayabank.ph/savings/&quot;&gt;Savings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;P1,410,598.76&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we have time deposits. Time deposits are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fixed-incomesecurity.asp&quot;&gt;fixed-income securities&lt;/a&gt; — contracts with a principal, interest rate, and maturity date. In this case, time deposit account owners deposit a principal, from which they receive back in full plus interest by the maturity date. The principal must not be touched by the depositor until the maturity date. Consequences for withdrawal from the time deposit account depend on the product being offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, BPI has a number of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bpi.com.ph/personal/bank/time-deposit-accounts&quot;&gt;time deposit products&lt;/a&gt;. The simplest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bpi.com.ph/personal/bank/time-deposit-accounts/5-year-plan-ahead&quot;&gt;Plan Ahead Time Deposit&lt;/a&gt; is a 5 year contract with a &lt;strong&gt;P50,000&lt;/strong&gt; minimum deposit. Unfortunately, the website delegates interest rate offerings to the individual branches, so one has to consult a branch to find out the interest rate for this product. Another BPI time deposit product, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bpi.com.ph/personal/bank/time-deposit-accounts/peso-auto-renew&quot;&gt;Auto Renew Time Deposit&lt;/a&gt; has interest rates readily available, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Required Daily Balance to Earn Interest&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;35 days&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;63 days&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;91 days&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;182 days&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;365 days&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Php 50,000 — Php 499,999&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.2500%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.2500%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3750%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3750%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Php 500,000 — Php 999,999&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3750%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Php 1,000,000 — Php 4,999,999&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.3750%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Php 5,000,000 and above&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5000%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.6250%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.6250%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7500%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7500%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one can see, the maximum interest one can earn from this time deposit product is &lt;strong&gt;0.75%&lt;/strong&gt;, available only through a 1-year maturity period on a Php &lt;strong&gt;5,000,000&lt;/strong&gt; balance. This is not a small chunk of change, especially with Philippine wages. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://psa.gov.ph/statistics/occupational-wages-survey&quot;&gt;PSA&lt;/a&gt;, the average wage in 2022 was P&lt;strong&gt;18,423&lt;/strong&gt;. Forget saving — to even earn P5m on that kind of wage, one needs to work for 22.6 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Maya’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.maya.ph/s/article/How-much-interest-will-my-money-earn-with-Time-Deposit-Plus&quot;&gt;Time Deposit Plus&lt;/a&gt; product offers &lt;strong&gt;5.5%&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;6%&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;5.75%&lt;/strong&gt; interest rate based on maturity periods of 3/6/12 months, with a deposit amount of P&lt;strong&gt;5,000&lt;/strong&gt; — P&lt;strong&gt;1,000,000&lt;/strong&gt;. Additionally, one can open 5 Time Deposit Plus accounts on a single Maya account to effectively earn &lt;strong&gt;6%&lt;/strong&gt; interest on a maximum of Php &lt;strong&gt;5,000,000&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a much more flexible product than BPI’s, and it offers massively higher returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Maya Time Deposit Plus technicality&lt;/summary&gt;
Technically, the &lt;i&gt;base interest rate&lt;/i&gt; on Time Deposit Plus accounts is &lt;b&gt;3.5%&lt;/b&gt;. The &lt;b&gt;6%&lt;/b&gt; comes from adding the &lt;i&gt;base interest rate&lt;/i&gt; and a &quot;&lt;i&gt;boosted interest rate&lt;/i&gt;&quot;, the latter only being activated when the balance in a Time Deposit Plus account reaches an arbitrary &quot;&lt;i&gt;target amount&lt;/i&gt;&quot; set by the user on the creation of the account. This is a bit weird to me, as the target amount can extremely low given that Maya still allows you to deposit past your target amount and earn interest the boosted interest. I assume it&apos;s part of their &quot;Personal Goals&quot; feature in the Maya app. Of course, these companies want you to feel as though you are making responsible financial decisions by labelling all their products as such and making it part of their brand. Nevertheless, it doesn&apos;t take away functionality and freedom, so it can simply be ignored.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other banks also offer time deposit products, but they’re similar enough to BPI’s and Maya’s products that they’re not worth covering. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bdo.com.ph/jp/mobile/personal/accounts/time-deposit/peso-time-deposit&quot;&gt;BDO&lt;/a&gt; offers up to 0.25% for everything below P1m. MetroBank has an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metrobank.com.ph/accounts/time-deposit/online-time-deposit&quot;&gt;“Online Time Deposit”&lt;/a&gt; that says to offer up to 4.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another product is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pagibigfund.gov.ph/Membership_ModifiedPagIBIG2.html&quot;&gt;Modified Pag-IBIG II Savings&lt;/a&gt; (MP2) account. They label it as a savings account, but it has a 5-year maturity period. 70% of Pag-IBIG’s annual net income goes towards Pag-IBIG Savings account holders as dividends, proportioned on contribution. Of course, this means the “interest rate” isn’t fixed, but rather, derived from the performance of the Pag-IBIG Fund. Since its inception in 2011, the MP2 product has returned anywhere from &lt;strong&gt;4.58%&lt;/strong&gt; in 2013 to its high of &lt;strong&gt;8.11%&lt;/strong&gt; in 2017. 2023’s return was &lt;strong&gt;7.05%&lt;/strong&gt;. Being dependent on the annual earnings of the Pag-IBIG Fund, returns are not fixed and hold within them a certain amount of risk. The product can outperform Maya Time Deposit Plus rates one year, and also barely protect you from inflation the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.treasury.gov.ph/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/RTB-30-Flyer.pdf&quot;&gt;Retail Treasury Bonds 30&lt;/a&gt; (RTB30), on the other hand, is a fixed-income security based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnb.com.ph/index.php/investment-opportunities/treasury-bonds&quot;&gt;treasury bonds&lt;/a&gt;. They have a 5-year maturity period and offer a fixed rate of &lt;strong&gt;6.25%&lt;/strong&gt; annual return. You deposit the principal once, and interest is credited to you quarterly until the bond matures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RTB30s have the advantage of being fixed-rate and essentially zero-risk — after all, they quite literally represent debt the government owes you. If the Republic of the Philippines is unable to pay off its debt to you, well, the Republic has fallen, and there is no use dabbling and worrying about fancy financial instruments when your country has already collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fixed return of &lt;strong&gt;6.25%&lt;/strong&gt; offers a clearer picture of the gains one can make, as opposed to a product like MP2. It is important to note however that MP2, being backed by Pag-IBIG, is still relatively low-risk and less volatile than commodities and stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all the information I had to talk about. Everything here I’ve discussed was a result of a weeks’ worth of messy Google searches, Reddit post readings from obscure subreddits, and rewatchings of The Big Short. Honestly, it’s been extremely entertaining. I’m excited to learn more about how the money system works and how best I can take advantage of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently, I’ve become semi-obsessed (slight exaggeration) with finance topics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">trivial math boredom</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/12/18/trivial-math-boredom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="trivial math boredom" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/12/18/trivial-math-boredom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/12/18/trivial-math-boredom.html">&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you wanted to compute for the following integral:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
\int sin^Nx \, \mathrm{d}x
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span&gt; \(N = 2n + 1, n \in \mathbb{Z}\)&lt;/span&gt;. In English, you want to get the integral of the sine function raised to an odd integer power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have to represent the integrand in a form wherein we can perform &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integration_by_substitution&quot;&gt;u-substitution&lt;/a&gt;. We can do so by separating one of the sines in the exponential:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
\int \sin^{2n+1}x \, \mathrm{d}x = \int \sin^{2n}(x)\sin(x) \, \mathrm{d}x
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then, using the identity &lt;span&gt;\(\sin^{2}x = 1 — \cos^{2}x\)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
\int \sin^{2n}(x)\sin(x) \, \mathrm{d}x = 
\int (\sin^{2}(x))^{n}\sin(x) \, \mathrm{d}x =
\int (1-\cos^{2}(x))^{n}\sin(x) \, \mathrm{d}x
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we can set &lt;span&gt;\(u = \cos x, \mathrm{d}u = -\sin{x}\mathrm{d}x\)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
\int (1-\cos^{2}(x))^{n}\sin(x) \, \mathrm{d}x = 
-\int (1-u^{2})^{n} \, \mathrm{d}u
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you can stop here, but I didn’t. I wanted to get a closed form solution (or rather, as close to closed form as possible).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;On the use of &quot;closed form&quot;&lt;/summary&gt;
I&apos;m well aware that &quot;closed form&quot; is not the appropriate term here, but I wanted to use it to express the idea of a solution that is simply plug-and-play. Leaving the integral as is would require extensive work for N &amp;gt; 2.

As for &quot;extensive work&quot;, I mean something that requires a CAS to do more than just simple integer multiplication.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveniently enough, since &lt;span&gt;\((1 — u^2)^n\)&lt;/span&gt; is a binomial, we can simply use the binomial theorem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
(x + y)^n = \sum_{k=0}^{n} \binom{n}{k} x^{n-k} y^k
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our binomial &lt;span&gt;\((1 — u^2)^n\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; would correspond to \(1\), and \(y\) would correspond to \(-u^2\):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
(1 -u^{2})^n = \sum_{k=0}^{n} \binom{n}{k} 1^{n-k} (-u^2)^k
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which, when using the formula \(\binom{n}{k} = \frac{n!}{k!(n-k)!}\), as well as removing the redundant \(1^{n-k}\) (as 1 raised to any integer is 1), results in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
(1 -u^{2})^n = \sum_{k=0}^{n} \frac{n!}{k!(n-k)!} (-u^2)^k
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this is simply the expansion of a binomial, which is a summation of terms each with a real coefficient and \(u\) raised to an integer power, when we substitute this back into the integral, we can simply use the power rule of integration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
\int \sum_{k=0}^{n} \frac{n!}{k!(n-k)!} (-u^2)^k \, \mathrm{d}u
=
\sum_{k=0}^{n} \frac{n!}{k!(n-k)!(2k+1)} (-u^2)^{k+1}
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and there we have it. An expression for \(\int sin^Nx \, \mathrm{d}x\) that requires nothing more than simple arithmetic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Let’s say you wanted to compute for the following integral:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">pedagogy</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/05/01/pedagogy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="pedagogy" /><published>2023-05-01T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-05-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/05/01/pedagogy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/05/01/pedagogy.html">&lt;p&gt;Trigonometry is a field of mathematics concerning functions that deal with angles (sine, cosine, secant). Don’t be fooled by this relatively humble description, however (I believe I’ve committed a heinous crime by describing trigonometry that way) — as it is some of the most important mathematics to have ever been done, and has countless applications across the fields of physics and engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the gravity with which trigonometry holds within the mathematical world, it is universally hated by math students across all grade levels and continents. If trigonometry is such an important subject, and is one that does not require extensive knowledge of to be useful in its various applications in physics and engineering, why does it receive so much hate? Of course, the answer lies within the actual teaching of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;i hate trig why do i need this in my life&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rory! 78 • 19 (@conansstar) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/conansstar/status/1650856176014225409?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 25, 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;i fucking hate trig who invented this shit its disgusting&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; rai 🇵🇭 (@padsplswin) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/padsplswin/status/1651451214968811520?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 27, 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my own experience as a high school student, trigonometry is taught like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedagogy/sohcahtoa.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are taught this “SOH-CAH-TOA” mnemonic, to memorize parts of a triangle, and then blindly plug in numbers into a calculator to obtain the result that you want. Of course students of trigonometry hate it — this teaches them nothing about what trigonometry actually is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trigonometry is a lot easier to think about when you relate it to &lt;strong&gt;circles&lt;/strong&gt; — not triangles. Picture a perfect circle with radius 1, a point on that circle, and a number &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;d&lt;/code&gt;. This number &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;d&lt;/code&gt; represents the angle in degrees that point has with respect to the x-axis — feel free to play around with it and observe how the point moves around the circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.desmos.com/calculator/kb00lt2vme&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;min-height:200px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this circle is embedded into a Cartesian plane with its center at the origin. What if we were to add another point that stays put with respect to the x-axis, but mimics the original point’s motion along the y-axis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.desmos.com/calculator/jiczpiougo&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;min-height:200px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how this point moves along the y-axis in an oscillating, &lt;strong&gt;wave-like&lt;/strong&gt; pattern. What if we were to do the same, but for motion along the x-axis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.desmos.com/calculator/jk50yty8n1&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;min-height:200px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let’s remove the circle, and graph the motion of these points as we change the angle, with the x-axis representing the angle and the y-axis representing each point’s respective magnitude. By “magnitude”, I mean the y-value of the point that mimics motion along the y-axis, and the x-value of the point that mimics motion along the x-axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.desmos.com/calculator/xqhibek8lz&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;min-height:200px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out, the point that mimics the motion along the y-axis represents the &lt;strong&gt;sine&lt;/strong&gt; curve, and the point that mimics the motion along the x-axis represents the &lt;strong&gt;cosine&lt;/strong&gt; curve! Finally, we have a tangible representation for what these functions actually model! As you increase the degree of the angle, the sine function represents the y-value or the “height” of the point that you end up at, while the cosine function represents the x-value or the “distance from the origin” of the point that you end up at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I can only do so much with Desmos embeddings and text. For a much clearer explanation of the concepts discussed above, watch Grant Sanderson’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/yBw67Fb31Cs&quot;&gt;excellent video&lt;/a&gt; on the topic. He explains it much like I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem that students run into when learning trigonometry is the switch from degrees to radians. For many students, degrees are intuitive — sure, their values may be arbitrary, but they benefit from familiarity. Radians, on the other hand, is an unfamiliar standard of measurement — students often question what the significance of π in representing angles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick lies by switching our perspective of where the angle “exists” instead to the length of the arc tracing the rightmost edge of the circle to any arbitrary point on the circle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/pedagogy/radians.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might recall that angles are typically represented by that small arc near the center of the circle — what I want you to do now is to focus instead on the much larger arc represented by the circumference of the circle. Then, imagine a point on the topmost part of the circle — instead of representing that angle as 90 degrees, we now represent it by the arc length running from the rightmost part of the circle to the topmost, which you’ll observe to be exactly a quarter of the total circumference. With a radius of 1, this would be \(\frac{\pi}{2}\). Of course, we can’t always assume that the radius will be one, which is why we need to generalize this measurement — instead of saying the angle is \(\frac{\pi}{2}\), we say it is \(\frac{\pi}{2}\) radiuses, or &lt;em&gt;radians&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tangent aside (pun not intended), the conclusion that I want you, the reader, to arrive at, is that in a learning environment, we cannot present knowledge as-is. Most knowledge, as you might observe, does not exist “as-is” — it has a history, it has motivations, it has a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; for being in that form. If we do not fully explain &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; certain knowledge came to be, the &lt;em&gt;motivation&lt;/em&gt; behind the knowledge existing in the first place, and the &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; the knowledge exists as it does today, then we fail to teach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to say that although I’ve never attended a university-level class in an actual college setting, I’m an avid viewer of recorded college lectures online and I’ve observed professors dedicate portions of their lecture to present the motivations behind teaching a certain subject. While this is a step in the right direction, the unfortunate truth is that a significant amount of teachers today, &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; in the foundation years that are the elementary and middle school stages, do not perform this simple task — and by doing so, they rob students of crucial knowledge that provides a foundation for all their future thinking to rest upon. What’s even more unfortunate, is that some teachers can’t help it — they themselves were victims of teachers that failed to do this simple task.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Trigonometry is a field of mathematics concerning functions that deal with angles (sine, cosine, secant). Don’t be fooled by this relatively humble description, however (I believe I’ve committed a heinous crime by describing trigonometry that way) — as it is some of the most important mathematics to have ever been done, and has countless applications across the fields of physics and engineering.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the hedonic treadmill</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/04/30/the-hedonic-treadmill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the hedonic treadmill" /><published>2023-04-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-04-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/04/30/the-hedonic-treadmill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2023/04/30/the-hedonic-treadmill.html">&lt;p&gt;Greenland is arguably one of the most beautiful countries on Earth. It’s home to some of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://kids.nationalgeographic.com/geography/countries/article/greenland&quot;&gt;beautiful icy landscapes&lt;/a&gt; and picturesque cities, and has the lowest population density of any country. Life in Greenland is peaceful, calm, quiet — a tranquil oasis in the desert of modern excess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/the-hedonic-treadmill/greenland.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
Pictured above is the landscape of Nuuk, the capital of and most populous city in Greenland.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except it’s got one dark secret — it has the highest suicide rate in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently stumbled upon this fact from this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LJzmFINLL6g&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; of a man that fulfills his childhood dream of visiting Greenland. He’s well aware of this grim statistic, interviewing a peaceful man that reveals his own suicidal tendencies, among several of his own family members and friends that have fallen to this serious disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although a little taken off guard, once I fully acknowledged the situation I began to see how such a population with such a peaceful exterior could have such a prevalent happiness problem — among the mindless routine, the loud silence, and the calm loneliness, who wouln’t crack a little? Of course, it’s a little more complicated than that — Greenland has a well-known &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7480488/&quot;&gt;alcoholism&lt;/a&gt; problem, among other things — but it nonetheless brings up an interesting discussion. If even in the most peaceful place on Earth, man cannot be happy, then where?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hedonic treadmill is an observed psychological tendency of humans to return to a “status quo” level of happiness after experiencing major changes in lifestyle — regardless of the magnitude of these changes. We experience this ourselves everyday — buying new things, getting your dream job, even being able to retire and live a life of luxury, grows stale with time. The short-lived burst of happiness we gain from this lifestyle transition doesn’t have to last merely days or weeks, but even months and years. The hedonic treadmill explains a significant amount of human history and behavior, such as colonialism, the industrial revolution, and capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, what the hedonic treadmill powers is this irrational desire for growth, for the evolution and the pimpification of our lifestyles, to cut down and smoke trees and pump water and build buildings and play games and drive cars to do our important jobs and drink drinks and laugh laughs. Biologically speaking, we should have been happy with hunting and gathering. Biologically speaking, the fucking agricultural revolution should have been enough. However, because of this simple cognitive quirk that fuels discontentment and funds programs to accumulate more and more STUFF, combined with the intellectual capacity to split the fucking atom, do we have the entirety of human history. Laid out for the aliens and higher powers to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, everyone is different. Not everyone falls victim to the hedonic treadmill, and some have a unique gift for turning a blind eye to it. Buddhism — heck, even Christianity before it got twisted and deformed into its modern perverted form designed to fund megachurches, along with other major world religions — are examples of this. Unfortunately, the West flaunted its bodacious material breasts for the rest of the world to be captivated by, and suckle on the breastmilk of endless growth and development. Thus, blind the people become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps technology can help? Surely technolgy can save us all? Cut down the trees, we’ve got solar panels on standby? Mine the coal, pump the oil, train the large natural language models, design the eco-friendly houses of the future — we don’t have to stop growing, for we’ve technology the saviour! This pattern of thinking can be likened to using matchboxes to put out a fire — a tiny chance you’ll actually put out the fire, but an overwhelmingly large chance you’ll just make a bigger fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically I’m part of the problem myself. You see, computer programming and mathematics — specifically the subfield that is AI — are my hobbies. You might be thinking “AI?! The thing that is quite literally the biggest threat to our position as king of the food chain?! That AI?! You’re writing about the redundancy of contemporary society and you dabble in AI?!”. In fact, you probably are thinking that, because as I’m writing this I’m questioning my own credibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/the-hedonic-treadmill/society-meme.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
If you&apos;re chronically online, you&apos;re well aware of this meme. If not, well — just know that if you sound like the above, then this meme is for you.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I have no idea how to solve this problem or the next move in my life. I’ll sit passively like the coward I am and watch as human history unfolds itself. Who knows, maybe this whole artificial intelligence being the end of the Anthropocene isn’t entirely true. Maybe we can still buy new things. Maybe we can still &lt;em&gt;grow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
This rant is partially inspired by Scott Alexander&apos;s excellent blog post entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/07/30/meditations-on-moloch/&quot;&gt;Meditations on Moloch&lt;/a&gt;. You should check it out, it&apos;s a lot more coherently written than this one.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Greenland is arguably one of the most beautiful countries on Earth. It’s home to some of the beautiful icy landscapes and picturesque cities, and has the lowest population density of any country. Life in Greenland is peaceful, calm, quiet — a tranquil oasis in the desert of modern excess.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">drive and meaning</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/12/22/drive-and-meaning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="drive and meaning" /><published>2022-12-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-12-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/12/22/drive-and-meaning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/12/22/drive-and-meaning.html">&lt;p&gt;If you asked me a year ago what my purpose in life was, I would’ve told you that I wanted to build great and cool things (greatness is optional — coolness is required). I would’ve told you that the driving force behind my existence was to joust with interesting intellectual challenges that the universe likes to throw at humanity. I wanted to be on the frontlines of history, to create things that impact as many human lives as possible. I didn’t necessarily want to be remembered, but to live my life in a manner in which I die peacefully, knowing I lived as much as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this as my foundation, I very easily accepted the ideas promoted by George Hotz. A slightly crazed, highly motivated individual with immense technical skill and an approach to thinking that I personally found unique as to be a breath of fresh air. Although Hotz, and other individuals like him, namely Elon Musk, preach about cooperation in the scientific and technical communities, their philosophy is one that is highly individualistic — just in a mankind vs. nature way. To paraphrase Hotz, the ultimate win in life is to “beat nature” and “escape the simulation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I absorbed his philosophy, I started to want to be him. He lived in San Francisco, in close proximity to other highly motivated individuals performing highly impactful work. His trade of choice, computer science (specifically artificial intelligence and cyber security), is also mine. His claim to fame — being the first to jailbreak the iPhone, and then the PS3 — I found inspiring in a twisted, peculiar way. Although I’m not above praising — and at times even worshipping — tech companies, I found this gesture to be deeply satisfying; a highly intellectual “fuck you” at bureaucracy, and a reminder of the stark power of the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, that sheer, raw ego is at the core of my current predicament. I used to associate intensely with this ideal — that life is one long series of opportunities to “beat nature”; that it was humanity against the universe. Don’t get me wrong, this isn’t an anti-environmentalist take — I have, am, and always will love nature. What this philosophy instead proposes is that our greatest meaning in life is to conquer life itself — to hyper-optimize the game of biology, to have a quasi-infinite amount of power, energy, and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m not so sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My love for science never came from a drive to solve problems — rather, it was born out of a love for perception. Ever since I was a little kid, I loved perceiving the world simply for the sake of perception. Bring me to a park, and I’ll just stare at the trees and the plants — first from a macro scale, and then a micro scale, where I can appreciate the incredibly detailed, incredibly eventful orchestra of biology and life happening all around us; on a leaf of a small plant, to the bark of a tree, to a stick on the ground, and the ant hill next to it. Bring me to a beach? I’ll stare at the sand underwater just to observe the shimmer patterns. I’ll rub my hands through the sand, feeling all the rocks and shells, and imagine how all those rocks and grains of sand were once part of a larger geological structure, broken off and eroded by the titanic forces of tidal patterns over millions of years. I’ll swim to the furthest point out into the sea, and hover still in the water — sensing the coldness of the water on my skin, the strength of the current ever so slightly tugging at my limbs, and I feel myself connected to the entire ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perception is also the driving force behind my love for math. Mathematics, when you understand it not as a stiff set of rules, but an artistic expression of the universe in all of her beauty and grace, is almost capable of convincing oneself that there must exist a divine artist. Alas, I am not religious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I am now thoroughly convinced that the mentality that I adopted from Hotz and many other intellectual heroes of mine — an egotistical, anthropocentric perspective — is incompatible with me. I want to &lt;em&gt;perceive&lt;/em&gt; the universe, not necessarily &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt; its game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further build upon this idea, what I think to be a lethal combination in a highly competent individual is both an anthropocentric view of the world and tunnel vision. A competent person (or a collection of competent people) with tunnel vision  can very easily solve the wrong problem. By solving the wrong problem, one can lose a small piece of the body of things that make them human. Have virtually infinite control over chemistry that you can simulate any taste with the right combination of chemical compounds? You get obesity, addiction, and you restrict yourself to artificially constructed cuisines that you ignore all the exotic tastes that nature can provide, and you most likely reject the vast culinary history that made up the ethnicity you were born into, instead selecting globally consistent, globally boring food concocted in a monochrome lab. Construct A.I. models capable of replicating manmade art? Although still woefully incapable, you introduce the world to the terrifying prospect that not even art, something we thought was core, fundamental, and immovable from the human condition, is safe from the overextending reach of machine automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, the blind pursuit of optimization and growth is not what drives me in life and dictates my everyday conduct anymore. I’m much more secure in myself, my pride, and my ego that I’ve allowed myself to accept that maybe all I want to be in this life is a passive observer; a true scholar of the universe. To be clear, this does not mean I do not want to build great things; I still do, but I will always hold closely in my mind the ethical implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/drive-and-meaning/zei_and_his_books.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Professor Zei and his books &lt;/summary&gt;
Pictured above is Professor Zei, refusing to budge from his place in the mystical Spirit Library of Wan Shi Tong, containing all the knowledge in the world, even as it crumbles around him.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads me to a tricky dilemma — do I still pursue artificial intelligence research, or not? On what hand, I find A.I. fascinating — the fact that the application of basic mathematical and statistical concepts can produce such complex behavior is something that I find to be simply wonderful. But as AI continuously advances (AI art and NLP models, to be precise), I began to slowly realize how much of an existential crisis AI poses on the human race. I am still a firm believer that AI can find its safe application within human society, but as it continues to demonstrate its weaponizability, I grow increasingly concerned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">If you asked me a year ago what my purpose in life was, I would’ve told you that I wanted to build great and cool things (greatness is optional — coolness is required). I would’ve told you that the driving force behind my existence was to joust with interesting intellectual challenges that the universe likes to throw at humanity. I wanted to be on the frontlines of history, to create things that impact as many human lives as possible. I didn’t necessarily want to be remembered, but to live my life in a manner in which I die peacefully, knowing I lived as much as I could.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the smartphone software scene is a joke</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/08/21/the-smartphone-software-scene-is-a-joke.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the smartphone software scene is a joke" /><published>2022-08-21T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-21T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/08/21/the-smartphone-software-scene-is-a-joke</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/08/21/the-smartphone-software-scene-is-a-joke.html">&lt;p&gt;The smartphone as it exists today is a cornerstone of society. Everyone that isn’t an extremist, in crippling poverty, or a child, has one. So why is smartphone software so bad?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to purchase a new smartphone (in 2022), you have two options — buy into the Apple ecosystem, or buy into the Google ecosystem. Neither is a terribly good choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The App store takes a 30% fee on all in-app purchases of apps that make over $1 million a year in revenue. If your app doesn’t make over $1 million a year, they take “just” 15%, out of the goodness of their hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30% is an insane margin. A real estate agent has a commission percentage of around 5-6%. A real estate agent has to convince a customer to make what is probably the single biggest expense of said customer’s life, only to take a measly 5-6% cut. Apple takes 30% by giving you the “privilege” of being part of their walled garden of an ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads app developers that don’t have a 30% or even a 15% profit margin to direct users to a &lt;strong&gt;website&lt;/strong&gt; every time they want to make a purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Google side, even though they have the same bracketed “app store tax” of 15% and 30% for under and below $1 million/year respectively, you at least have the option to bypass the Play Store entirely, and download a raw &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.apk&lt;/code&gt; file from one of the dozens &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.apk&lt;/code&gt; websites on the internet, many of which are extremely suspicious. However, no one but technically-sound people do this, and only when they already know they want the app — people that browse the Play Store will never be able to know the app exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire reason Apple and Google can charge an insane margin for in-app purchases in the first place is the fact that they hold a duopoly on the smartphone operating system market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On iOS, you can’t uninstall many of the core Apple apps, like Safari, Stocks, etc. All browsers on the App store are simply &lt;strong&gt;reskins&lt;/strong&gt; of Safari. That means that if you’re shopping for a browser on iOS, you’re not really picking what browser you’re going to use, but what company you’re going to voluntarily give your data to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, on Google, you can’t uninstall YouTube, Chrome, Google Play services, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, but you think to yourself — this sounds awfully familiar. It sounds exactly like the Windows or macOS predicament that desktop users have experienced for years! Surely, the solution to the mobile operating system dilemma, much like the desktop operating system dilemma, would be to install a free, open operating system? Like Linux?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, sure, you could fill a top 10 list of mobile operating systems not named iOS or Android pretty easily. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itsfoss.com/open-source-alternatives-android/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcmag.com/picks/break-away-from-android-ios-7-free-open-source-mobile-oses-to-try&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://alternativeto.net/software/android/&quot;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt; have done so (surprise surprise, some of these are Android-based), but have fun with the app selection. Mobile app developers build almost exclusively for Android and iOS, because Google and Apple make it extremely easy to, with Google’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.android.com/studio&quot;&gt;Android Studio&lt;/a&gt; and Apple’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/xcode/&quot;&gt;XCode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desktop Linux, meanwhile, lives on, despite the dominance of Windows and macOS simply because the desktop app development ecosystem is much less centralized and much more cross-platform, and because (and I can’t believe I’m about to say this), desktop Linux is &lt;strong&gt;easier&lt;/strong&gt; to install on a desktop or laptop compared to installing an alternative OS on an Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt; Speculation &lt;/summary&gt;
I speculate that it&apos;s also relatively easy to build a Linux port of a desktop app, simply because macOS is based on BSD, and BSD is Unix-like.
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install an alternative OS on an Android, you first have to attain &lt;strong&gt;root&lt;/strong&gt; privileges. That’s right — most smartphone owners don’t even have full &lt;strong&gt;power&lt;/strong&gt; over their smartphones. Attaining root on an Android was relatively straightforward in the early 2010s, but as the years passed by, newer Android phones became harder and harder to root. Rooting also comes with the wonderful consequences of voiding your warranty, so have fun with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you’ve attained root, you need to flash a custom ROM (Read Only Memory) on the device, provided by the developers of the operating system you’re trying to install. After that, the steps are OS-dependent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, you need just flash any Linux distribution on any regular old USB, plug it into your desktop, reboot into the USB, and install it from there. After that, it’s not as smooth sailing — Linux is notorious for hardware compatibility issues with certain components, but hey — at least you installed the damn OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last gaping hole on the smartphone software scene is the update life cycle. Apple usually provides 5 or more years of updates for its iPhones — that covers iOS generations and security updates. That’s not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Google provides a measly 2 years. That means that after 2 years, any major cybersecurity vulnerability discovered in the last Android version that your smartphone uses will not get patched. That means if you value your security, especially if you do mobile banking, you need to purchase a new smartphone every 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Note on iOS&lt;/summary&gt;
On iOS, this process is known as &quot;jailbreaking&quot;.
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duopoly that Google and Apple has on the smartphone OS market has lead to terrible software design choices, lack of freedom, and possibly exposes users of this critical technology to hackers if they don’t barf up a couple hundred US dollars every 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re rich (or American), you probably don’t care. You probably &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; already get a new phone every 2 years. But for the majority of the world that spends $200-$300 on their device and uses it for 6, it’s not as easy. And because of the lack of root privileges, there’s software in your device that you can’t control — and when you purchase a cheap phone, it’s most likely a Chinese one, and they’re not exactly the role model of respecting user privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The smartphone as it exists today is a cornerstone of society. Everyone that isn’t an extremist, in crippling poverty, or a child, has one. So why is smartphone software so bad?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">power of nonlinearity</title><link href="https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/08/20/power-of-nonlinearity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="power of nonlinearity" /><published>2022-08-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/08/20/power-of-nonlinearity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://journal.francisdb.net/2022/08/20/power-of-nonlinearity.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skip to the next section if you’re unfamiliar with the underlying neural network mathematics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neural network is a fundamental idea that powers many AI systems we have today. It has been scaled up to tackle hard problems such as natural language understanding, object recognition, driving, and many other abilities thought to be exclusive only to humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details closed=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Rant &lt;/summary&gt;
The idea that intelligence is exclusive to a carbon-based neural network such as the brain is absurd. Any sort of computation that the brain performs to transform electrical signals into coherent thought can and will be done by silicon. The problem is figuring out the computations in the first place.
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The following is a multi-layer feedforward neural network as it is commonly visualized, and how they’re commonly explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/nn.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Neural net&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single “neuron” in this network has a “weight” and a “bias”. The neuron takes in a real-valued number as input, and transforms it according to the following equation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
$$\begin{aligned}
n(x)=n_w⋅x+n_b
\end{aligned}$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It then feeds the result to the next layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about neural networks this way is messy. Instead, we take a different route. Let’s think about the input as being a vector, and we pass this vector input to each layer as a whole, instead of thinking about passing separate numbers to each neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, if you work out the math, you’ll realize that the linear transformations being performed by each neuron, if you consider them as a whole, is analogous to a matrix vector product. In fact, it is exactly a matrix vector product — we aggregate the weight vectors in each neuron to one large weight matrix, and each bias in each neuron to one large bias vector. Then, the computation being done by a single layer can be represented elegantly with this one-liner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
$$l(x)=l_W⋅x+l_b,$$
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \(l_W\) is the weight matrix, and \(l_b\) is the bias vector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, neural networks can be simply thought of as a series of linear transformations to data!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-linear-transformations-are-useful&quot;&gt;Why linear transformations are useful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A linear transformation is a function that takes in a coordinate, and maps it to a different coordinate in Euclidean space. However, the transformation is only classified as linear if grid lines remain &lt;em&gt;parallel&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;evenly spaced&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matrices are linear transformations — performing a matrix vector product with a 2x2 matrix on a 2-vector results in another 2-vector. 2-vectors are just vectors with 2 dimensions; therefore, you can extend the idea of a coordinate to a 2-vector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can combine linear transformations to perform prediction on data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, take the following scatter plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/plot1.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wanted to come up with our own series of linear transformations to categorise this data, we might come up with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rotation&lt;/strong&gt; — Imagine the linear boundary between both groups. We rotate the data such that that linear boundary is now horizontal:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/plot2.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Translation&lt;/strong&gt; — Now, with the rotation being done, our next transformation is not actually a linear transformation, but rather a translation along the y-axis such that both groups are separated by the y-axis, through the use of a bias vector instead of a weight matrix:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/plot3.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Squeeze”&lt;/strong&gt; — Now, we use a singular matrix to transform the data from 2D Euclidean space to 1D Euclidean space, preserving the y-coordinate:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/plot4.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, our hypothetical neural network’s outputs can be easily interpretable — anything less than 0 is part of the “red” class, and anything above 0 is part of the “blue” class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three linear transformations don’t need to be in separate layers, either — they can be easily combined to one layer, by multiplying them all: \(L=l_3⋅l_2⋅l_1\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-how-about-more-complex-data&quot;&gt;But how about more complex data?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all data is linearly separable by default. For example, observe this scatter plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/spiral.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no obvious linear pattern we can observe here. Therefore, we have to &lt;strong&gt;make&lt;/strong&gt; our linear transformations &lt;strong&gt;non-linear&lt;/strong&gt;, and we do that by interspersing them with nonlinear functions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
$$l(x)=σ(l_W⋅x+l_b)$$
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where \(σ\) is any arbitrary nonlinear function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this added functionality, here’s a visualization of how a nonlinear function can &lt;strong&gt;transform&lt;/strong&gt; nonlinear data into linear data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/power-of-nonlinearity/spiral.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linearly separable data is much easier to deal with!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we showed that neural networks (&lt;em&gt;at least, the feed-forward neural network&lt;/em&gt;) are not what they are commonly compared to — biological neural networks. Instead, they are a series of linear transformations in the form of matrix vector products, interspersed with nonlinearities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fundamental idea of composing “non-linear linear transformations” has led to many breakthroughs in the field of AI; namely, &lt;a href=&quot;https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2012/file/c399862d3b9d6b76c8436e924a68c45b-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;convolutional neural networks&lt;/a&gt; in the field of computer vision, &lt;a href=&quot;https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2017/file/3f5ee243547dee91fbd053c1c4a845aa-Paper.pdf&quot;&gt;transformer networks&lt;/a&gt; in the field of natural language understanding, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioinf.jku.at/publications/older/2604.pdf&quot;&gt;LSTMs&lt;/a&gt; in the field of general time-series forecasting. With parameter counts reaching up to the hundreds of &lt;strong&gt;billions&lt;/strong&gt;, it is not hard to see that this basic idea of stacking transformations can tackle much higher-dimensional data such as images and natural language.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Skip to the next section if you’re unfamiliar with the underlying neural network mathematics</summary></entry></feed>